Harold Bell Wright papers, 1890-1946
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Harold Bell Wright papers, 1890-1946
MS 360
Wright, Harold Bell
Collection consists of correspondence, professional writings, and miscellaneous materials by or about Harold Bell Wright. The majority of the collection consists of sermons, handwritten manuscripts, and magazine publications written by Wright. The bulk of the correspondence is professional correspondence between Wright and his publishers. Miscellaneous materials include photographs, newspaper clippings, and ephemera.
12.75 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None
Biographical Note
Harold Bell Wright was America's leading romance author from 1903 to about 1923. It is estimated that of his nineteen books published between 1903 and 1942, as many as ten million copies were sold. Harold Bell Wright was born in Rome, N.Y. to parents William A. and Alma Watson Wright on May 4, 1872. After his mother died when he was ten years old, and his father abandoned him, he lived several years with various relatives and strangers, working for shelter and scraps of food. Wright attended Hiram College in Hiram, Ohio until the late 1890s when he was forced to leave school to combat a serious illness. He relocated to Missouri where he regained his health and started his preaching career. From 1897 to 1908 he served as a minister in the Christian Church (Disciples of Christ). His preaching took him to Pierce City, Missouri; Pittsburg, Kansas; Kansas City, Missouri; Lebanon, Missouri; and lastly to Redlands, California. In 1902 Wright wrote his first book, That Printer of Udell's, which he read to his Pittsburg, Kansas congregation, one chapter per week. What That Printer was published in 1903, sales were good enough that Wright almost immediately started writing Shepherd of the Hills. When that story was published in 1907, its sales broke publishing records and established Wright as America's top-selling author. The following year he left the ministry to pursue his promising writing career. While living in the Imperial Valley, Wright wrote several books including The Winning of Barbara Worth, his highest selling title. In 1920, after many years of illness, Wright moved to Tucson, Arizona where he believed the climate aided in his recovery. In Tucson he wrote several of his novels, such as When a Man's a Man {[1916]. In 1935 he returned to California, this time to San Diego where he resided until his death on May 24, 1944.
Organization
This collection is organized into three series
Series I: Correspondence, 1912-1944
Series II: Writings, 1890-1942
Series III: Miscellaneous Materials, 1923-1946
Scope and Content Note
Collection consists of the papers of Harold Bell Wright. Correspondence, professional writings, and the miscellaneous materials are by or about Harold Bell Wright. There are a limited number of writings by his son Gilbert Wright, aka John Lumbar [sic] [Lebar], including a co-authored novel with his father. The majority of the collection consists of sermons, handwritten manuscripts, and magazine publications written by Harold Bell Wright. The bulk of the correspondence is professional correspondence between Harold Bell Wright and his publishers.
Miscellaneous materials include photographs, newspaper clippings, and ephemera. The photographs are photocopies of a 1925 scrapbook which include photographs of Harold Bell Wright, Mrs. Wright, their home in Tucson, Arizona, and some of their travels. The majority of newspaper clippings, which are also photocopies, relate to Harold Bell Wright. The ephemera consists of printed material and postcards collected by or about Harold Bell Wright.
Wright, Harold Bell, 1872-1944.; Wright, Norman H.; Wright, Gilbert.; Kitt, Katherine, Florence, 1876-1945.; Mullenix, R.C.; Novelists, American-20th Century.; Tohono Oodham Indians Folklore.; Tucson (Ariz.) - History.; Sermons.; Novels.; Plays.; Correspondence.; Film Scripts.; Ephemera.; Scrapbooks.; Periodicals.
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1912-1944
  - Subseries 1: Personal Correspondence
    - Norman Wright (son of Harold Bell Wright) incoming correspondence, February 24, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Norman Wright outgoing correspondence, February 10, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Gilbert Wright (son of Harold Bell Wright) incoming/outgoing correspondence, 1931-1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Gilbert Wright outgoing, 1931-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Extended family incoming correspondence, 1912-1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Extended family outgoing correspondence, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 2: Professional Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous incoming professional correspondence, November 26, 1919 - April 30, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous outgoing professional correspondence, December 1919 - October 1941, no date (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Katherine Kitt incoming correspondence, June 16, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Katherine Kitt outgoing correspondence, June 6, 1925 - June 7, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - D. Appleton & Company Publishers incoming correspondence, 1923-1931 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - D. Appleton & Company Publishers outgoing correspondence, 1928-1931 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Harper & Brothers Publishers incoming correspondence, 1931-1933 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Harper & Brother Publishers outgoing correspondence, 1931-1933 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Library of Congress copyright notices, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - R.C. Mullenix incoming correspondence, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - R.C. Mullenix incoming correspondence, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - R.C. Mullenix outgoing correspondence, March 16, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series II: Writings, 1890-1942
  - Subseries 1: Sermons
    - Sermons delivered in Pittsburg, Kansas, December 1890 - November 1901 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous, March 6, 1898 - November 1901 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous A - H, No date (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous I - R, No date (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous S - Z, No date (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous, no titles, No date (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Evangelistic sermons, 1902 - 1906 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Evangelistic Series I, volume 1 - 9, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Evangelistic Series II, volume 1 - 9, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Evangelistic Series II, volume 10 - 18, 1906 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Evangelistic volume 1907, incomplete set, March 10, 1907 - May 5, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Evangelistic volume 1907, incomplete set, May 12, 1907 - July 21, 1907, no date (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Evangelistic Series- Saying of the Cross, notes, No date (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Evangelistic and Christian Index to Sermons, Addresses, and Talks, February 1907 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Christian Sermons 1905-1906, no date (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Christian Series- The Problem of Problems, numbers 4 and 6, 1905 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Christian volume, 1907 February 3, 1907 - April 7, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Christian volume, 1907 April 14, 1907 - June 2, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Christian volume, 1907 June 9, 1907 - August 4, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Christian Addresses and Funeral, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 2: Novels
    - That Printer of Udell's, outline, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - That Printer of Udell's, first writing, No date (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - That Printer of Udell's, hardbound inscribed edition, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - The Calling of Dan Matthews,, first writing, cover, 1908 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - The Calling of Dan Matthews,, first writing, chapters 1-5, 1908 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - The Calling of Dan Matthews, first writing, chapters 6-11, 1908 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - The Calling of Dan Matthews, first writing, chapters 12-18, 1908 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - The Calling of Dan Matthews, first writing, chapters 19-25, 1908 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - The Calling of Dan Matthews,, first writing, chapters 26-29, 1908 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - The Calling of Dan Matthews, first writing, chapters 30-35, 1908 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - The Calling of Dan Matthews, first writing, chapters 36-42, 1908 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Their Yesterdays, first writing, cover, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Their Yesterdays, first writing, chapters 1 - 10, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Their Yesterdays, first writing, chapters 11-20, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Their Yesterdays, first writing, chapters 21 - 26, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - The Uncrowned King, 1910 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - The Winning of Barbara Worth, outline, 1910 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - The Winning of Barbara Worth, first revision, 1911 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - The Eyes of the World, cover and outline, 1910 - 1912 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - The Eyes of the World, outline part A, 1910 -1912 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - The Eyes of the World, outline part B, 1910-1912 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - The Eyes of the World, outline part C, 1910-1912 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - The Eyes of the World, outline part D, 1910-1912 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - The Eyes of the World, outline part E, 1910-1912 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - The Eyes of the World, first revision, 1914 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - The Eyes of the World, final revision, 1914 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - The Eyes of the World, inscribed hardback edition, 1914 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - When a Man's a Man, inscribed hardback edition, 1917 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Helen of the Old House, inscribed hardback edition, 1921 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - The Mine with an Iron Door, 1923 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - A Son of His Father, argument and character outline, No date (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - A Son of His Father, first outline, No date (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - A Son of His Father, synopsis and second outline, No date (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - A Son of His Father, first revision, No date (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - A Son of His Father, first writing, No date (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - A Son of His Father, inscribed hardback edition, 1925 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - God and the Groceryman, synopsis, No date (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - God and the Groceryman, miscellaneous writings and notes, No date (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - God and the Groceryman, first writing, 1926-1927 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - God and the Groceryman, first revision, 1926-1927 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - God and the Groceryman, inscribed hardback edition, 1927 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Stories Long Ago Told:, Papago Indian Legends, individual stories, May 23, 1921 – February 4, 1925, No date (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Stories Long Ago Told:, Papago Indian Legends, individual stories, May 23, 1921 – February 4, 1925, No date (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Stories Long Ago Told:, Papago Indian Legends, individual stories, May 23, 1921 – February 4, 1925, No date (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Stories Long Ago Told: Papago Indian Legends, first writing and revision, No date (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Stories Long Ago Told: Papago Indian Legends,second revision, No date (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Stories Long Ago Told(Huh-Kew-Kah): Papago Indian Legends, No date (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Stories Long Ago Told: Papago Indian Legends, glossary of Papago words used by Harold Bell Wright, No date (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Stories Long Ago Told: Papago Indian Legends, Papago words, No date (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Stories Long Ago Told: Papago Indian Legends,Papago vocabulary, No date (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Exit,copy with revisions, 1927 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Exit,first revisions, No date (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Exit,scenario, No date (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Exit,final revision, March 1930 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Exit,printer's copy, march 1930 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Exit,inscribed hardbound edition, 1930 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Ma Cinderella, synopsis, No date (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Ma Cinderella,first writing, March 27, 1931 – October 30, 1931 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Ma Cinderella, revision, 1931 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - The Devil's Highway, novel by Harold Bell Wright and John Lumbar (aka Gilbert Wright), first revision, No date (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - The Devil's Highway, novel by Harold Bell Wright and John Lumbar (aka Gilbert Wright), final revision, No date (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - To My Sons, cover, No date (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - To My Sons, page 1-132, No date (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - To My Sons, page 133-244, No date (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - To My Sons, page 245-431, No date (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - To My Sons, page 432-558, No date (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - To My Sons, page 559-end, No date (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - To My Sons, revision, 1932 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - To My Sons, revision, handwritten notes, 1932 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - A Boy, A Girl and a Penguin, handwritten notes, No date (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - A Boy, A Girl and a Penguin, first writing, 1937 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - A Boy, A Girl and a Penguin, revision, No date (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - A Boy, A Girl and a Penguin, final revision, 1938 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - A Boy, A Girl and a Penguin, typed final copy, No date (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Molly Picket's Man, miscellaneous writings, No Date (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Molly Picket's Man, first writing, 1938 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Molly Picket's Man, first revision, 1938 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - The Man Who Went Away, work plan, idea, No Date (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - The Man Who Went Away, outline notes, No Date (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - The Man Who Went Away, argument, plan, working notes, No Date (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - The Man Who Went Away, outline I, No Date (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - The Man Who Went Away, 1932-December 2, 1941 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - The Man Who Went Away, work plan, idea, February 16, 1942 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - The Man Who Went Away, work plan, idea, No Date (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Between You and Me, first writing, No date (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Between You and Me, finished copy, No Date (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - This Rebellious Generation, first writing, No Date (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - This Rebellious Generation, first writing, No Date (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - This Rebellious Generation, final revision, No Date (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - What About God?, first writing, No Date (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - What About God?, revision, No Date (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 3: Plays
    - Blacksmith, first revision, 1915 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Blacksmith, finished copy, 1915 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - The Salt of the Earth, Tucson revision, No date (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - The Salt of the Earth, inscribed to son Paul Wright from Harold Bell Wright, No date (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - An Outline for a three act play, 1930-1931 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Exit: A Play in Three Acts, No date (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Exit: A Play in Three Acts, No date (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Exit: A Play in Three Acts, No date (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Exit: A Play in Three Acts, No date (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 4: Short Stories
    - A Desert Santa Claus, first writing and first revision. Published in Ladies Home Journal December 1927, 1910,1927 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Born of the Desert, 1918 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Skee Dee or The Whole Doughnut, 1918 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Why I Did Not Die, 1924 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - A House with Windows, No date (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - A House with Windows, notes and article clippings, No date (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - A House with Windows, notes, No date (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - A House with Windows, No date (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Basket of Clips, No date (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Bud and the Bishop, No date (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - Little Talks About Big Things, No date (Box 25, Folder 11)
    - The Mystery of Lone Mountain, No date (Box 25, Folder 12)
    - My N.B. Book, No date (Box 25, Folder 13)
    - One Afternoon, No date (Box 25, Folder 14)
    - Pages from God's Other Book, No date (Box 25, Folder 15)
    - This and That, No date (Box 25, Folder 16)
    - Untitled, No date (Box 25, Folder 17)
    - Untitled, No date (Box 25, Folder 18)
    - Untitled, No date (Box 25, Folder 19)
  - Subseries 5: Articles and Speeches
    - The Royal Family of Tomorrow, September 20, 1915 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - One Hundred Percent Men, 1918 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Boy Scout's Drive, September 16, 1923 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - A Question of Patriotism, November 1923 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Do You Believe in Immortality? Why?, January 17, 1926 January 30, 1927 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Dedication of Temple of Music and Art, Tucson Arizona, January 30, 1927 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - As It Looks to the Cross Anchor, April 28, 1928 (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Untitled, March 1919 (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - Untitled, April 1928 (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - Untitled, January 12, 1923 (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - The American Way, No date (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - To the El Centro High School, No date (Box 26, Folder 12)
    - An Example of Desert Thirst, No date (Box 26, Folder 13)
    - "Keeping" Christmas, No date (Box 26, Folder 14)
    - The School Kids Call Him Tony, No date (Box 26, Folder 15)
    - Untitled, No date (Box 26, Folder 16)
    - Untitled, No date (Box 26, Folder 17)
    - Untitled, No date (Box 26, Folder 18)
  - Subseries 6: Poems
    - Born of the Desert, No date (Box 26, Folder 19)
    - Born of the Desert, No date (Box 26, Folder 20)
  - Subseries 7: Magazine Publications
    - American Magazine, February 1918 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - American Magazine, June 1924 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - American Magazine, June 1928 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Cosmopolitan, February 1932 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Cosmopolitan, March 1932 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Cosmopolitan, April 1932 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Cosmopolitan, May 1932 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Cosmopolitan, June 1932 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Cosmopolitan, December 1932 (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Cosmopolitan, January 1933 (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Cosmopolitan, February 1933 (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - Cosmopolitan, March 1933 (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - Outdoor America, November 1923 (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - Outdoor America, June 1928 (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - McCall's, March 1925 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - McCall's, April 1925 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - McCall's, May 1925 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - McCall's, June 1925 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - McCall's, July 1925 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - McCall's, August 1925 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - McCall's, September 1925 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - McCall's, October 1925 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - McCall's, January 1927 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - McCall's, February 1927 (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - McCall's, March 1927 (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - McCall's, April 1927 (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - McCall's, May 1927 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - McCall's, June 1927 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - McCall's, July 1927 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Ladies Home Journal, December 1927 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Pictorial Review, December 1930 (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Pictorial Review, January 1936 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Good Housekeeping, July 1932 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Physical Culture, April 1931 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Physical Culture, July 1931 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Physical Culture, October 1931 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Physical Culture, November 1931 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Physical Culture, December 1931 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Physical Culture, January 1932 (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Physical Culture, February 1932 (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Physical Culture, March 1932 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 8: Motion Picture Scripts
    - The Eyes of the World, working copy, No date (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - The Shepherd of the Hills, completed and copyrighted, 1919 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 9: Miscellaneous Notes
    - Untitled, July, no year (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, No date (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 10: Writings by Gilbert Wright (Son of Harold Bell Wright)
    - The Principles of Ethericity, 1932 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Screen Plays, 1936, no date (Box 31, Folder 6)
- Series III: Miscellaneous Materials, 1923-1946
  - Ephemera for The Man Who Went Away, No date (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Ephemera for The Man Who Went Away, 1923-1928, No date (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Ephemera relating to Harold Bell Wright, No date (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Ephemera including printed materials and postcards, No date (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, October 1927-January 14, 1939; No date (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, No date (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings, The Book of Knowledge, 1946 (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Photocopied scrapbook and photographs, 1925,No date (Box 32, Folder 8)